<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<record xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/xsd/primo/primo_nm_bib" xmlns:sear="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/xsd/jaguar/search">
  <control>
    <sourcerecordid>ks65h991878</sourcerecordid>
    <sourceid>nduspec_ead</sourceid>
    <recordid>nduspec_eadks65h991878</recordid>
    <sourceformat>XML</sourceformat>
    <sourcesystem>Other</sourcesystem>
  </control>
  <display>
    <type>archival</type>
    <title>Abel Blanchard family correspondence</title>
    <creator>Benjamin Blanchard, 1786 - 1869</creator>
    <creator>Lewis Blanchard, 1788 - 1847</creator>
    <creator>Mark Blanchard, 1790 - 1839</creator>
    <creator>Abel Blanchard, Jr., 1798-1867, 1798 - 1867</creator>
    <creator>Barnes Blanchard, 1807 - 1878</creator>
    <format>48 folders; 1 container; .42 linear feet</format>
    <subject>New York [State] -- History -- 1775-1865.</subject>
    <subject>New York [State] -- History -- War of 1812.</subject>
    <subject>New York [State] -- Social life and customs -- 1775-1865.</subject>
    <subject>Frontier and pioneer life -- New York [State].</subject>
    <subject>Erie Canal [N.Y.] -- History</subject>
    <subject>Allegany County [N.Y.] -- History</subject>
    <description>A group of around 50 manuscripts retained by the Abel Blanchard family of Peacham, Vermont. Most are personal letters dating from the 1810s and 20s, written to Vermont by family members newly migrated to Canada or western New York state.</description>
    <language>Collection material in English</language>
    <coverage>1795-1852</coverage>
    <coverage>(bulk 1810-1836)</coverage>
    <availlibrary>$$INDU$$LHESB$$1Special Coll.$$2MSN/EA 5031[In-Library Use Only]$$Savailable$$YSPEC$$ZGEN</availlibrary>
    <citation>Abel Blanchard Family Correspondence, Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame.</citation>
    <lds01>Aquisition Information: &lt;acqinfo encodinganalog="583"> Acquisition and Processing Note The Blanchard correspondence was purchased by the Hesburgh Libraries in 2011 from Michael Brown Rare Books of Philadelphia (List 112, Item 7). Arranged and described 2011, by Scott W. Young. Finding aid 2011-12, by Scott W. Young and George Rugg.</lds01>
    <lds03>&lt;scopecontent encodinganalog="520"> Scope and Content Note The Blanchard correspondence consists primarily of personal letters directed to the homestead at Peacham by family members in Canada and New York state. The principal authors are Benjamin Blanchard (9 letters); Lewis (8 letters); Mark (6 letters); Abel, Jr. (5 letters); and Barnes (6 letters). Twenty-seven of the 42 letters in the collection were written prior to 1820. Internal evidence suggests that most of the letters written home by the five principal authors, especially during the 1810s, have survived in the collection. Because the Blanchards wrote only occasionally, their letters typically provide an overview of recent movements, activities, and intentions (as well as those of their brothers, when known). Before settling as farmers, the Blanchards pursued a great variety of (frequently seasonal) occupations, most notably brickmaking (which may have been a family trade). There is a great deal in the letters on business prospects in the Holland Purchase, on prices and the accessibility of markets (in the period before western New York was opened up by the completion of the Erie Canal). In the letters of 1812-1815 there is frequent mention of the War of 1812 and its profound impact on residents of western New York and Canada. There is mention of internal improvements, like the Erie and Oswego canals and a railroad line through Centerville. Later letters show a preoccupation with evangelical Christianity that is not previously evident; this may or may not be attributable to the religious revivals that swept the "burned-over district" in the 1820s and after. The collection also includes a number of other family letters, as well as five land deeds of uncertain relevance to the rest of the material. &lt;/scopecontent></lds03>
    <lds03>Arrangement Note: &lt;arrangement encodinganalog="351"> Arrangement Note Correspondence (folders 1 to 42) is arranged chronologically, one item per folder. Miscellaneous material (folders 43 to 48) is arranged in the same manner. &lt;/arrangement></lds03>
    <lds04>&lt;bioghist encodinganalog="545"> Capt. Abel Blanchard (1761-1827) was a native of Hillsborough County, New Hampshire, the son of Benjamin Blanchard and Keziah Hastings. After serving in the Revolutionary War Blanchard married Elizabeth Eastman of Concord (1784). Around 1785 the couple moved to what is now Caledonia County in northeast Vermont, to the town of Peacham, where Blanchard served as captain of the militia and, on several occasions in the 1780s and 90s, as selectman. Abel and Elizabeth Blanchard had 10 children who survived to adulthood: Ruth (1785-1862); Benjamin (1786-1869); Lewis (1788-1847); Mark (1790-1839); Hazen (1792-1867); Judith (1793-1891); Clarissa (1796-1851); Abel, Jr. (1798-1867); Cynthia (1802-1881); and Barnes (1807-1878). Of the Blanchard sons, Benjamin, Lewis, Mark, Abel, and Barnes all left Peacham, unmarried, in their late teens or early twenties (Benjamin by 1809; Lewis in 1809; Mark in 1811; Abel in 1817; and Barnes in 1827). Each, with the apparent exception of Lewis, married 3-5 years after leaving. Hazen Blanchard, the fourth son, remained with his parents on the family farm at Peacham. On leaving Vermont the Blanchards sought to establish themselves at various locations in Upper and Lower Canada (the present provinces of Ontario and Quebec) and in New York state. By 1811 Benjamin and Mark Blanchard had acquired land near Batavia, in the Holland Purchase (which comprised what are now the ten westernmost counties of New York). By the 1820s the Blanchards and their families had congregated around Centerville, in present-day Allegany County, where they raised grain, produce, and livestock. &lt;/bioghist></lds04>
    <availinstitution>$$INDU$$Savailable</availinstitution>
    <availpnx>available</availpnx>
  </display>
  <links>
    <linktofa>$$Uhttps://rbsc.library.nd.edu/finding_aids/und:ks65h991878$$DFull description / Finding Aid</linktofa>
  </links>
  <search>
    <creatorcontrib>Benjamin Blanchard, 1786 - 1869, 1786-1869</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard Benjamin , 1786 - 18691786 1869</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard, Benjamin, 1786-1869</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Lewis Blanchard, 1788 - 1847, 1788-1847</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard Lewis , 1788 - 18471788 1847</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard, Lewis, 1788-1847</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Mark Blanchard, 1790 - 1839, 1790-1839</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard Mark , 1790 - 18391790 1839</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard, Mark, 1790-1839</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Abel Blanchard, 1798 - 1867, 1798-1867</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard Abel , 1798 - 18671798 1867</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard, Abel, Jr., 1798-1867</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Barnes Blanchard, 1807 - 1878, 1807-1878</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard Barnes , 1807 - 18781807 1878</creatorcontrib>
    <creatorcontrib>Blanchard, Barnes, 1807-1878</creatorcontrib>
    <title>Abel Blanchard family correspondence</title>
    <description>A group of around 50 manuscripts retained by the Abel Blanchard family of Peacham, Vermont. Most are personal letters dating from the 1810s and 20s, written to Vermont by family members newly migrated to Canada or western New York state.</description>
    <description>&lt;scopecontent encodinganalog="520"> The Blanchard correspondence consists primarily of personal letters directed to the homestead at Peacham by family members in Canada and New York state. The principal authors are Benjamin Blanchard (9 letters); Lewis (8 letters); Mark (6 letters); Abel, Jr. (5 letters); and Barnes (6 letters). Twenty-seven of the 42 letters in the collection were written prior to 1820. Internal evidence suggests that most of the letters written home by the five principal authors, especially during the 1810s, have survived in the collection. Because the Blanchards wrote only occasionally, their letters typically provide an overview of recent movements, activities, and intentions (as well as those of their brothers, when known). Before settling as farmers, the Blanchards pursued a great variety of (frequently seasonal) occupations, most notably brickmaking (which may have been a family trade). There is a great deal in the letters on business prospects in the Holland Purchase, on prices and the accessibility of markets (in the period before western New York was opened up by the completion of the Erie Canal). In the letters of 1812-1815 there is frequent mention of the War of 1812 and its profound impact on residents of western New York and Canada. There is mention of internal improvements, like the Erie and Oswego canals and a railroad line through Centerville. Later letters show a preoccupation with evangelical Christianity that is not previously evident; this may or may not be attributable to the religious revivals that swept the "burned-over district" in the 1820s and after. The collection also includes a number of other family letters, as well as five land deeds of uncertain relevance to the rest of the material. &lt;/scopecontent></description>
    <general>AllDocuments</general>
    <general>A group of around 50 manuscripts retained by the Abel Blanchard family of Peacham, Vermont. Most are personal letters dating from the 1810s and 20s, written to Vermont by family members newly migrated to Canada or western New York state.</general>
    <general>&lt;bioghist encodinganalog="545"> Capt. Abel Blanchard (1761-1827) was a native of Hillsborough County, New Hampshire, the son of Benjamin Blanchard and Keziah Hastings. After serving in the Revolutionary War Blanchard married Elizabeth Eastman of Concord (1784). Around 1785 the couple moved to what is now Caledonia County in northeast Vermont, to the town of Peacham, where Blanchard served as captain of the militia and, on several occasions in the 1780s and 90s, as selectman. Abel and Elizabeth Blanchard had 10 children who survived to adulthood: Ruth (1785-1862); Benjamin (1786-1869); Lewis (1788-1847); Mark (1790-1839); Hazen (1792-1867); Judith (1793-1891); Clarissa (1796-1851); Abel, Jr. (1798-1867); Cynthia (1802-1881); and Barnes (1807-1878). Of the Blanchard sons, Benjamin, Lewis, Mark, Abel, and Barnes all left Peacham, unmarried, in their late teens or early twenties (Benjamin by 1809; Lewis in 1809; Mark in 1811; Abel in 1817; and Barnes in 1827). Each, with the apparent exception of Lewis, married 3-5 years after leaving. Hazen Blanchard, the fourth son, remained with his parents on the family farm at Peacham. On leaving Vermont the Blanchards sought to establish themselves at various locations in Upper and Lower Canada (the present provinces of Ontario and Quebec) and in New York state. By 1811 Benjamin and Mark Blanchard had acquired land near Batavia, in the Holland Purchase (which comprised what are now the ten westernmost counties of New York). By the 1820s the Blanchards and their families had congregated around Centerville, in present-day Allegany County, where they raised grain, produce, and livestock. &lt;/bioghist></general>
    <general>&lt;scopecontent encodinganalog="520"> The Blanchard correspondence consists primarily of personal letters directed to the homestead at Peacham by family members in Canada and New York state. The principal authors are Benjamin Blanchard (9 letters); Lewis (8 letters); Mark (6 letters); Abel, Jr. (5 letters); and Barnes (6 letters). Twenty-seven of the 42 letters in the collection were written prior to 1820. Internal evidence suggests that most of the letters written home by the five principal authors, especially during the 1810s, have survived in the collection. Because the Blanchards wrote only occasionally, their letters typically provide an overview of recent movements, activities, and intentions (as well as those of their brothers, when known). Before settling as farmers, the Blanchards pursued a great variety of (frequently seasonal) occupations, most notably brickmaking (which may have been a family trade). There is a great deal in the letters on business prospects in the Holland Purchase, on prices and the accessibility of markets (in the period before western New York was opened up by the completion of the Erie Canal). In the letters of 1812-1815 there is frequent mention of the War of 1812 and its profound impact on residents of western New York and Canada. There is mention of internal improvements, like the Erie and Oswego canals and a railroad line through Centerville. Later letters show a preoccupation with evangelical Christianity that is not previously evident; this may or may not be attributable to the religious revivals that swept the "burned-over district" in the 1820s and after. The collection also includes a number of other family letters, as well as five land deeds of uncertain relevance to the rest of the material. &lt;/scopecontent></general>
    <general>Writing to his father, Lewis mentions that he has been absent from home for a year or more and has had "as good luck . . . as can be expected for a young man to start out into the world with out anything . . . ." Also mentions that he has heard by letter that his brother (Benjamin) and cousin are safely arrived at Osnabruck, Upper Canada (a township on the St. Lawrence), hoping to make bricks.</general>
    <general>Writing to Thomas Estman (Eastman) at Peacham, Lewis tells of his travels to and within Canada over the past year: from Peacham to Montreal, up and down the Grand (Ottawa) River, a stay in Quebec, and return to Montreal.</general>
    <general>Lewis relays news of his brother Benjamin's brickmaking enterprise at Osnabruck, and gives a positive report of the state of trade locally: ". . . there was never known to be so much Shipping in Montreal ever sinse it was Settled . . . ."</general>
    <general>Lewis reports that he has been upriver to Osnabruck, and plans to return to tend a store for a man named Wells.</general>
    <general>Benjamin reports on the progress of his brickmaking venture, remarking that he and his cousin Samuel have produced a total of 175,000 bricks, selling at 6 dollars per thousand. Also mentions he is planning a trip through the Holland Purchase of western New York state, and thence home to Peacham. Lewis appears to have "a very good business" in his arrangement with Wells.</general>
    <general>Benjamin writes that he and his brother Mark have each bought land in Nunda in the Holland Purchase. They plan to make bricks at a kiln in nearby Batavia during the winter months, and farm their lots the rest of the year. Talks at length about the influx of settlers, especially Vermonters, into the area, and its access to markets in Buffalo, Pittsburgh, and Montreal.</general>
    <general>Mark writes his younger brother of his feelings on leaving home and family.</general>
    <general>Benjamin reports that both he and his brother Mark took jobs teaching school the previous winter. Mark is now gone to the "Alegany"; Benjamin plans to stay at Lima (east of Batavia) and make bricks for a house being built by a Mr. John Morgan. Again speaks of the region's superior access to markets, via the Genesee River, Lake Ontario, and the St. Lawrence.</general>
    <general>Lewis speaks of the raising of a regiment of Canadian militia, with an eye to possible war with the United States. Notes the terms of enlistment, and the large number of Americans who have volunteered (including an acquaintance, John Guy). Plans to spend the summer in Montreal; the harsh winter there, and commentary on prices.</general>
    <general>Mark discusses the local ramifications of the outbreak of war between Great Britain and the U. S., and his own membership in the militia. "[T]he people in this Country seem to be for war principally those that live on the frontier are a moving their families off every day . . . the Indian fever prevails all over the purchase they seem to be in agitation all the time in holding council among the tribes . . . the people are trying to cross over from Canada but are prohibited by the soldiers . . . the minuet men belonging to the Western District are called for and stationed at Buffaloe and Niagara except one company that belong to the Allegany I belong to that company we were warned the last of June a friday to start on wednesday it was a time they expected the British would cross but the Militia turn out from Batavia and from all parts . . . and quelled their fear . . . ."</general>
    <general>The author, driven from Canada by the war, describes his travels from Montreal to Utica. Reports on the continued success of Benjamin's brickmaking business in Lima, New York, and on Mark's status as a "minnet man". Mention of military drafts and the location and number of troops around the Great Lakes-St. Lawrence region.</general>
    <general>A report on the brothers' whereabouts in the winter of 1812-13: Benjamin is "tending Bar" at McCracken's Tavern in Batavia; Mark is a distiller at Caledonia, New York, and Lewis is teaching school at Avon, New York. Speaks of the spread of infectious disease among the U. S. troops at Buffalo.</general>
    <general>Lewis reports on his current occupation as a schoolteacher. He and his brothers Mark and Benjamin are all healthy, though it is very "sickly" in the western country; on the frontier, contagion typically begins among the soldiers. In an extended commentary, Lewis states that those who live on the frontier have been victimized by a war that he calls destructive, unjust, and unnecessary: ". . . never was their sutch destructtive mesher taken sens the United States was a nation you do not feel it in New England as the people doe in this Country . . . . O what a trieing seen must be to those that experences it to here the howling Savages voices reecoe [reecho] in the forress when before ware was declared, was the dwellings of our brethern and the voice of the ax men was heard the lowing of the ox but now that onse flourishing Country has become a sacrifice to the savages such are the consequences attending ware in this Country . . . ." Also, word that William Henry Harrison has been defeated by the Indians near Detroit.</general>
    <general>Mark notes that it has been two years since he left Vermont. He remarks on his military service, which included "one short campaign on Susquehannah". Criticizes American generals Hull and Smythe, and the decision to go to war "with an empty treasuary". Discusses his current occupation as a distiller, noting that distillers receive high wages in the region, amounting to thirty to forty dollars per month. Notes that money is plentiful in western New York, but that the disorder caused by the war has been destructive for the region.</general>
    <general>Benjamin reports the birth of a son and provides details of his sawing business. He also provides news of his brothers: Mark is a distiller in Geneseo, New York and Lewis is a sutler in the same place, serving a local regiment. As for the war, "it is very still times as present the Army has principally left Buffalo . . . ." Benjamins wife, Ruhanna Gleason Blanchard (m. 1814), writes the second half of the letter to her sister-in-law Clarissa, remarking on the difficulties she's experienced maintaining communication with family and friends since leaving Vermont.</general>
    <general>Mark complains of having received but one letter from home in nearly three years, and vows to write no more under such circumstances. His wife (Jerusha Spencer Blanchard, m. 1814) sends her regards.</general>
    <general>Lewis reports on his brickmaking, and notes that conditions are generally better since the declaration of peace.</general>
    <general>Writing from Fort George, Upper Canada, Benjamin informs his father that he and Lewis have secured a contract to make 250,000 bricks, to be sold at $5.25 per thousand, for an all-brick fort being constructed by the British on Lake Ontario near the Niagara River (Fort Mississauga). Eight employees have been hired, at wages of $16-20 a month. Benjamin expects to return to Nunda in October. He also notes local commodity prices: pork ranges from $25-30 per barrel, flour sells at $11 per barrel, and pine boards at $20 per thousand.</general>
    <general>Abel, Jr., reports on what is perhaps his first journey from home, to the town of Preble in central New York.</general>
    <general>Benjamin reports on that's spring's journey from Vermont back to Nunda. He is now in Canada, arriving to make bricks with his brother Lewis (who had remained in the area through the winter, chopping wood and digging clay). Business is slow in the absence of government contracts; Benjamin has hired a new group of seasonal employees at $11-13 per month. Commodity prices: pork is now starting at $35 per barrel and flour ranges from $9-10 per barrel.</general>
    <general>Scraps of news; Abel Jr. may head west in February.</general>
    <general>Personal news.</general>
    <general>A brief personal letter to Abel Blanchard from a niece in Maine.</general>
    <general>Benjamin reports that the town of Nunda has been divided, and he now resides in Pike. Much of the letter is given over to advice about possible legal difficulties arising from a land transaction in Vermont between Hazen and a man named Foster. The author also reports news of Abel Jr., who had been working with their brother Mark for the previous three months before traveling to meet Lewis at Fort George in Ontario. The author comments on the severe winter and its effect on food production and business in the region, saying "money is hard to get a hold of here at this time."</general>
    <general>Mark's wife Jerusha recently delivered a stillborn child, and Lewis has set out for Peacham. This is the first of the family letters headed Centreville (Centerville), which was set off from Pike in January 1819.</general>
    <general>Abel reports personal and family news to his sister, saying that their brother Lewis has informed him that their father is in a poor state of health and that Judith has joined the church in Peacham. Abel further reports that he and Lewis now own adjoining farmland in Centerville, and that Mark's wife Jerusha is ill.</general>
    <general>In a letter directed to her mother-in-law at Peacham, Jerusha describes her debilitated state.</general>
    <general>Benjamin reports that he is in good health and would like to see his father visit the family in western New York. Benjamin is now working with his brother Mark in harvesting and selling maple sugar. Also reports that brother Abel has married a woman from Centerville named Harriete Trail, and that the two intend to settle there. Benjamin's wife Ruhanna concludes the letter with personal news directed to Benjamin's sister Judith.</general>
    <general>Judith informs her sister and sister-in-law (Sally Burbank Blanchard, wife of Hazen) that she is safely arrived in Centerville. In an extended narrative, she describes her 11-day journey west across the state of New York. Included is a brief account of the newly completed Erie Canal (on which her party did not travel): [W]e stopt at Little falls to view the Canall which is north seeing what cost and labor there is in that little spot we crosed the canall 8 or 10 times saw boats filled with gentlemen and ladies some riding on the top some sitting in the fore part of the boat knitting and sewing . . . ." Judith goes on to give her impressions of the family, including her brothers, their wives, their children, and the new town in which they all live.</general>
    <general>Judith reports that she is now living with her brother Mark and taking care of his house, as his wife Jerusha has recently died. In the portion of the letter directed to her sister Cynthia and her brother's wife Sally, she discusses personal and family news.</general>
    <general>Mark describes his ten-day journey home to Centerville from Vermont, including a passage on the Erie Canal: . . . [M]onday morning at ten oclock I got to the western canal fifty miles below Utica waited about two hours for a boat had a very agreeable passage to Rochester where I arrived saturday morning I lived as well as I could wish aboard the boat for one shilling a meal and one cent a mile for passage the boat was loaded very heavy had a great many stops to make which is the reason of my being so long on the canal . . . ."</general>
    <general>The youngest Blanchard son describes his journey from home and the field labor he is performing for $13 per month. He is situated along the Middlesex Turnpike, about 75 miles northwest of Boston.</general>
    <general>Writing from the vicinity of Syracuse, Barnes reports that he is in good health following an ankle injury suffered in the spring. Goes on to mention construction of the Oswego Canal (linking the Erie Canal with Lake Ontario); French-Canadian, Irish, and German immigration into central New York; and the Anti-Masonic Party.</general>
    <general>Barnes notes that this letter is only the third he has written home since leaving Peacham in 1827. His present plan is to stay in Centerville for the summer to work land he has purchased for two and a half dollars per acre, ("the common price of land in the state of nature.)" Mark has a new house on his land, for which he still owes $100. Lewis and Abel, for their part, have partly paid off the deed on the land they own together. The author then addresses a separate section of the letter to his mother, telling her that despite his years of absence she remains dear to his heart.</general>
    <general>A letter concerning the settlement of the estate of one Ebenezer Davis.</general>
    <general>Barnes reports on local agricultural and commercial conditions. "English grain" came in well but prices for produce and beef are generally low: ". . . I suspect it is on account of an cessation of Business in our Markets Money is scarce more so then common produce is low of all Description . . . ." Lewis spent the summer making bricks. Also notes the general "contention and strife" provoked by disagreements between persons of different religious denominations.</general>
    <general>The author discusses his health and the health of his family, notably his wife, who has suffered from a "long complaint attended with much cough." Speaks at length about his relationship with his wife and about the role of religious faith during her illness.</general>
    <general>Barnes discusses a possible visit from his mother and muses on life in general, saying ". . . we Rise in the morning full of vig[or]ous hope and expectation and we find that our hopes are all Blasted and expectation are disappointed. . . ." The author also describes the recent harvest, saying that the cold and wet have led to unfavorable corn and wheat crops. Hopes that the area will benefit from the upcoming construction of a railroad from New York to Buffalo, running within 15 miles of Centerville.</general>
    <general>The author of this letter is unidentified.</general>
    <general>Writing in a religious vein, the author reflects at length on his life's experiences and his current regrets. He invites his brother to relocate to New York state, noting that land can be purchased for the reasonable price of $8 per acre. Notes that the Centerville area will benefit from the construction of a canal along the Genesee River and a railroad linking New York City with Lake Erie. To his mother specifically, the author reaffirms his affection and love.</general>
    <general>The author, writing to his grandmother, is a son of Benjamin Blanchard, born ca. 1827. He mentions a two-week revival meeting held in Centerville, attended by Lewis and Barnes and many other townspeople, but protested against by Abel.</general>
    <general>The author is probably Harriet Trail Blanchard, wife of Abel Blanchard, Jr. She invites her parents to visit, saying "We have such a Peacham settlement. It is just like getting among old neighbors."</general>
    <general>For a plot in Falmouth, Cumberland County, Maine.</general>
    <general>For a plot in Peacham, Caledonia County, Vermont.</general>
    <general>&lt;p/></general>
    <sourceid>nduspec_ead</sourceid>
    <recordid>nduspec_eadks65h991878</recordid>
    <recordid>ks65h991878</recordid>
    <toc>Letter. Lewis Blanchard, Montreal, Lower Canada, to Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. [Lewis Blanchard], Montreal, Lower Canada, to Mr Thomas Estman, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Lewis Blanchard, Montreal, Lower Canada, to Mr Able Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benjamin Blanchard, Osnabruck, Upper Canada, to Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Ben[jamin] Blanchard, Batavia, New York, to Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Mark Blanchard, Bata[via], New York, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benj[amin] Blanchard, Lima, New York, to Mr Jacob Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Lewis Blanchard, Montreal, Lower Canada, to Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Mark Blanchard, Nunda, New York, to Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Lewis Blanchard, Utica, New York to Mr Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Ben[jamin] Blanchard, Batavia, New York, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Lewis Blanchard, Lima, New York to Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Mar[k Blanchard], Caledonia, New York, to Mr Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benjamin Blanchard and Ruhanna Blanchard, Nunda, New York, to Abel Blanchard and Clarissa Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Mark Blanchard, Nunda, New York, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Lewis Blanchard, Lima, New York, to Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benjamin Blanchard, Fort George, Upper Canada, to Capt Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Abel Blanchard, Jr., Preble, New York, to Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benjamin Blanchard, Niagara, Upper Canada, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Abel Blanchard, [Jr.], Preble, New York, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Abel Blanch[ard, Jr.], Preble, New York, to Judah [Judith] Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Betsey Knight, Rumford, Maine, to Capt. Abel Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benj[amin] Blanchard, Pike, New York, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Abel Blanchard [Jr.], Centreville, New York, to Judith Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Abel Blanchard [Jr.], Centerville, New York, to Judith Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Jerusha Blanchard, n.p., to Mrs E[lizabeth] Blanchard, n.p.,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Benj[amin] Blanchard and R[uhanna] B[lanchard], Centerville, New York, to Capt Abel Blanchard and Judith B[lanchard], Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Judith Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Sally Blanchard and Cynthia Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Judith Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Abel and Elizabeth Blanchard, Cynthia Blanchard, and Sally Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Mark Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Judith Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Barnes Blanchard, Tyngsborough, Massachusetts, to Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Barnes Blanchard, Salina, New York, to Mr Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Barnes Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Hazen Blanchard and E[lizabeth] Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Earl Sawyer and Rufus Metcalf, Freedom, New York, to Mr Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Barnes Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Mr Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Mark Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Mr Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Barnes Blanchard, n.p., to Mr Hazen Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. "E T", Kingsville, Ohio, to Elizabeth Todd, Plymouth, Connecticut,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Barnes Blanchard, Centerville, New York, to Hazen Blanchard and Elizabeth Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. William Blanchard, Pike, New York, to Elizabeth Blanchard, Peacham, Vermont,</toc>
    <toc>Letter. Harriet Blanchard, Osceola, New York, to "Father and Mother", n.p.,</toc>
    <toc>Document. Land deed of sale, Abigail Brackett to William Holmes,</toc>
    <toc>Document. Land deed of sale, Enoch Knight to William Holmes,</toc>
    <toc>Document. Land deed of sale, William Holmes to Ezra Carter,</toc>
    <toc>Document. Land deed of sale, Josiah Shedd to William Holmes,</toc>
    <toc>Document. Land deed of sale, Nehemiah Bradlee et al to William Holmes,</toc>
    <toc>Manuscript. Poem, "I am in love",</toc>
    <rsrctype>archival</rsrctype>
    <searchscope>nduspec_ead</searchscope>
    <searchscope>NDU</searchscope>
    <scope>nduspec_ead</scope>
    <scope>NDU</scope>
    <alttitle>Guide to the Abel Blanchard Family Correspondence</alttitle>
    <lsr01>SPEC RBSC</lsr01>
    <lsr02>Blanchard Blanchard Blanchard Blanchard Blanchard Abel Blanchard family correspondence</lsr02>
    <lsr02>Abel Blanchard family correspondence Blanchard Blanchard Blanchard Blanchard Blanchard</lsr02>
    <lsr05>MSN/EA 5031</lsr05>
    <lsr05>MSN/EA5031</lsr05>
    <lsr05>MSN EA 5031</lsr05>
    <lsr05>MSN EA5031</lsr05>
    <lsr05>MSNEA5031</lsr05>
    <lsr05>MSNEA 5031</lsr05>
  </search>
  <sort>
    <title>abel blanchard family correspondence</title>
    <creationdate>1810</creationdate>
    <author>Benjamin Blanchard, 1786 - 1869</author>
    <lso01>1810</lso01>
    <lso02>MSN/EA 5031</lso02>
  </sort>
  <facets>
    <language>eng</language>
    <creationdate>1810</creationdate>
    <toplevel>available</toplevel>
    <prefilter>archival</prefilter>
    <prefilter>manuscript</prefilter>
    <rsrctype>archival</rsrctype>
    <rsrctype>manuscript</rsrctype>
    <library>HESB</library>
    <newrecords>20181020_934</newrecords>
    <frbrgroupid>7682774</frbrgroupid>
    <frbrtype>6</frbrtype>
  </facets>
  <dedup>
    <t>99</t>
  </dedup>
  <frbr>
    <t>99</t>
  </frbr>
  <delivery>
    <institution>NDU</institution>
    <delcategory>Physical Item</delcategory>
  </delivery>
  <ranking>
    <booster1>1</booster1>
    <booster2>1</booster2>
  </ranking>
  <addata>
    <aulast>Blanchard</aulast>
    <aufirst>Benjamin</aufirst>
    <aufirst>Lewis</aufirst>
    <aufirst>Mark</aufirst>
    <aufirst>Abel</aufirst>
    <aufirst>Barnes</aufirst>
    <addau>Blanchard, Benjamin, 1786-1869</addau>
    <addau>Blanchard, Lewis, 1788-1847</addau>
    <addau>Blanchard, Mark, 1790-1839</addau>
    <addau>Blanchard, Abel, Jr., 1798-1867</addau>
    <addau>Blanchard, Barnes, 1807-1878</addau>
    <date>1810</date>
    <risdate>1795-1852</risdate>
    <genre>archival</genre>
    <ristype>GENERIC</ristype>
    <abstract>A group of around 50 manuscripts retained by the Abel Blanchard family of Peacham, Vermont. Most are personal letters dating from the 1810s and 20s, written to Vermont by family members newly migrated to Canada or western New York state.</abstract>
    <cop>Notre Dame, IN</cop>
    <pub>Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, University of Notre Dame</pub>
    <objectid>MSN/EA 5031</objectid>
  </addata>
  <browse>
    <title>$$D Abel Blanchard family correspondence$$E Abel Blanchard family correspondence</title>
    <subject>New York (State) -- History -- 1775-1865.New York (State) History 1775-1865.</subject>
    <subject>New York (State) -- History -- War of 1812.New York (State) History War of 1812.</subject>
    <subject>New York (State) -- Social life and customs -- 1775-1865.New York (State) Social life and customs 1775-1865.</subject>
    <subject>Frontier and pioneer life -- New York (State).Frontier and pioneer life New York (State).</subject>
    <subject>Erie Canal (N.Y.) -- HistoryErie Canal (N.Y.) History</subject>
    <subject>Allegany County (N.Y.) -- HistoryAllegany County (N.Y.) History</subject>
    <institution>NDU</institution>
  </browse>
</record>
